Catholic Charities USA
The American Catholic Research Center and University Archives
1881(1920-2015)2015
The American Catholic Research Center and University Archives
Catholic Charities USA
367 linear feet; 295 boxes
This expansive and diverse assemblage of records displays nearly a century of national Catholic commitment to social thought and activism and consists of correspondence, minutes of the board of directors, committee and legislative files, surveys and studies, photographs and publications.
76
Historical Note
Catholic Charities USA (CCUSA) is a national association of local and diocesan Catholic charitable agencies founded as the National Conference of Catholic Charities (NCCC) on the campus of The Catholic University of America (CUA) in Washington, D.C. in 1910. The organization, which became CCUSA in 1986, has grown into one of the largest social welfare associations in the nation, and currently has 1,735 branches throughout the United States. More than 240,000 volunteers, staff, and board members comprise the Catholic Charities network, serving over 7.8 million people of all faiths yearly. The national office of Catholic Charities, USA, currently located in Alexandria, Virginia, consists of 40-50 staff members.
The NCCC was founded by a group of 17 laypersons and nine clerics to address the needs of the immigrant-swollen Catholic population in the United States. Thanks in part to the mass migration from Europe throughout the nineteenth century there were over 16,363,000 Catholics in the U.S. by 1910. Many of these individuals were in need of a variety of social services which at the time were provided by a vast but unorganized network of about 800 Catholic charitable institutions that provided care to the destitute, children, the sick, and the elderly, among others. Leaders in the St. Vincent de Paul Society, one of the most active of these Catholic organizations, realized that there was a need to gather this growing charitable network into an organization that could survey and coordinate activities, compare ideas, and communicate on a regular basis. Members of the Society provided the chief impetus in the lay population for the founding of NCCC. Particularly influential were two members of the Superior Council of New York City: Thomas Mulry, who served as Council President, Edmond Butler, a pioneer Society organizer with contacts in national charity networks, and Robert Biggs, a Baltimore Vincentian. Butler described the aim of the organization as: "a forum for closer union, mutual encouragement, dissemination of sound Catholic principles, more efficient protection of common Catholic interests, more abundant and accurate information concerning all forms of Catholic charities, the creation of helpful Catholic charity literature, and such other benefits as are likely to accrue from united Catholic effort." Among the key clerical figures in the founding of NCCC were Monsignor William J. Kerby of CUA and Monsignor D.J. McMahon of New York City, who had been discussing the establishment of a national charitable organization with the Vincentians for years. Brother Barnabas, of the Brothers of the Christian Schools in New York, however, provided the essential trigger for the first national conference. In a letter to Bishop Thomas Shahan, CUA Rector, Barnabas suggested Shahan start a "National Conference of Catholic Charities" that would bring together charity workers from across the U.S. Shahan agreed to lead the effort (he would serve as President of NCCC until 1929) and an organizing group held the first general meeting at Catholic University from September 25-28, 1910. Over the next decade the NCCC grew into an association of lay volunteers, and to a lesser extent, professional social workers and clergy. Catholic laywomen dominated the early membership, while the leadership was comprised of members of the St. Vincent de Paul Society.
Kerby's influence on the fledgling organization proved pivotal. While he served as secretary for only a decade, his application of progressive social work ideas to Catholic charitable practice was original and decisive in the formative years of the organization. Kerby challenged the individualistic terms in which early twentieth century Catholic charity was understood, downplaying the idea of poverty as a product of the individual's lack of thrift or misfortune and emphasizing a more systemic view of its origins. The "church's social work is directed more towards effects than toward causes" he noted in 1907, "toward personal action on the individual rather than on social forces; toward the spiritual more than the temporal." Seeking to "re-establish" the position of the individual in the broader society, Kerby advocated using social remedies to alleviate poverty. He embraced the progressive reforms of the period calling for child labor laws, fair wages, and public health reforms, but connected these reforms to the Catholic tradition.
Kerby's successor, Monsignor John O'Grady, was more aggressive and strategic in his leadership of NCCC. Kerby, courteous and reticent about his own role in the establishment of the national organization, maintained strong organizational relationships with the early leadership and lay volunteers of NCCC. O'Grady, who served as secretary in 1920 and remained at the helm of the NCCC for the next 41 years, sought to extend the influence of NCCC through further cultivation of professional charity workers and the strengthening of the diocesan branches. A central figure in the professionalization of Catholic social workers, he promoted the establishment of the Catholic University School of Social Work, serving as its first dean from 1934 until 1938. O'Grady, moreover, actively sought to exercise influence in government where charity for Catholics was concerned, meeting with countless government figures on issues related to child welfare, housing, and rural poverty.
Postwar era concerns ranged from support for legislative initiatives that fostered-rather than supplanted--private charitable agencies, to emphasis on Christian charity as the force behind Catholic social work in an era of increasing professionalization of the field. As times changed, local charities adapted their services to different populations in need. The 1960s saw emphasis on soup kitchens, housing, and service to the elderly. By the 1980s and 90s CCUSA's services became more wide-ranging, including refugee and immigration assistance, service to HIV/AIDS patients, and disaster relief.
For nearly a century, NCCC/CCUSA has served as the primary representative of Catholic charity in the United States. Summoning members of local Catholic charities together to discuss and compare their activities at national conferences, they have performed a communal and networking function. Sponsoring a range of publications and surveys, including the Catholic Charities Review (the Review ceased publication in 1975. Today, CCUSA publishes the Charities, USA magazine on a regular basis), they have served to disseminate the latest thought and development within the profession with a Catholic slant. Representing local Catholic charity agencies on a national level, they continue to influence public opinion and legislation that impacts the practice of charity in the U.S. The work of the national organization has continued to facilitate the professionalization of Catholic social work in the U.S., prompting local charities to conduct casework, train social workers, and standardize social work practices.
Scope and Contents
The records of Catholic Charities USA, known as the National Conference of Catholic Charities prior to 1986, is a large and diverse assemblage of materials ranging from correspondence and meeting minutes to photographs and other audiovisual materials.
The first series is titled Early Records, 1910-1918, in box 1. Included are 1910 meeting minutes and programs dated 1916-1918 as well as correspondence from first secretary, William J. Kerby, concerning the 1912 Report, the 1914 conference dues, and assorted issues in 1915. There is also a copy of the address of Samuel Gompers, President of the American Federation of Labor (AFL) to a Catholic University of America (CUA) class in 1916.
The second series is the Board of Directors Minutes and Related Papers, 1925(1925-1988)2004, filed chronologically, boxes 1-11. The Board was known as the Executive Committee prior to 1950 when an amended constitution changed the name of that of the Board of Directors. This series is divided into seven subseries. The first is Executive Committee/Board of Directors, 1925-1961, in boxes 1-3. The second is General and Executive Committee material, 1961-1986, in boxes 4-8. The third is Personnel Committee Files, 1963-1978, in box 9. The fourth is Bylaws Committee, 1962-1978, in box 10. The fifth is Health Affairs Committee, 1974-1978, in box 10. The sixth is Nominating Committee, 1979-1984, in boxes 10-11. The seventh and last is General and Miscellaneous, A-Z, 1965-2004, in box 11.
The third series is General Administration Files, 1920-2008, divided into six subseries. The first is the voluminous and alphabetical Subject Files, dated primarily 1920 to 1961, but with a few items dating to 1965, boxes 12-58 Of particular note here are folders related to the American Association for Organizing Family Social Work, the American Association of Social Workers, The Catholic University of America, the Child Welfare League, Community Chests and Councils, and the Federal Security Agency that later became the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW). This first subseries also includes files of Francis Mellen, Field Secretary, containing correspondence, membership material, and dissertation research files. Mellen was a CUA student under O'Grady and appears to be the only person to ever have held the title of 'Field Secretary' for NCCC and was involved in membership campaigns and field visits to various diocesan establishments. By 1934 there is evidence of a strained relationship with O'Grady and Mellen appears to have either resigned or fired that same year. The second subseries is another run of alphabetical Subject Files, dated 1961-2008, in boxes 58-76. The third is General and Miscellaneous Files, dated 1969(1990-2001)2001, and located in boxes 77-81. The fourth is Federal Organizations, 1937-1981, in boxes 82-89, that include U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW), 1961-1977; Summit Conference on Inflation, 1974; and White House conferences on various topics such as Aging, Nutrition, Health, Children, and Miscellaneous, 1937-1981. The fifth is Religious Organizations, 1960-1985, in boxes 90-97, which include Caritas Internationalis-International Confederation of Catholic Charities, 1967-1985; Coalition of National Voluntary Organizations, 1976-1980; Ladies of Charity, 1960-1982; National Catholic Welfare Conference (NCWC), later the United States Catholic Conference (USCC), 1961-1979; and Parish Social Ministry (Jerome Ernst), 1976-1979. The sixth and last subseries is Secular Organizations, 1961-1984, in boxes 98-110, which include Joint Action in Community Service (JACS), 1967-1982; National Association of Social Workers (NASW), 1967-1978, National Center for Voluntary Action (NCVA), 1969-1978, National Social Welfare Assembly, 1961-1967, and its successors the National Assembly for Social Policy and Development, 1967-1974; and the National Assembly of National Voluntary Health and Social Welfare Organizations, 1974-1980; United Community Funds and Councils of America, 1964-1970; United Way, 1970-1984; and the Urban Coalition-War on Poverty, 1964-1976.
The fourth series is Committee Files, 1920-1961, in boxes 112-182, is divided into ten subseries. The first is Topic-Business/Local Committees, 1920-1980, in boxes 112-134, and filed chronologically. Please note that there was a distinction between Topic-Business and Local Committees. Topic-Business were the general committees of the National Conference of Catholic Charities (NCCC) and their names changed frequently. They were noted as Topic Committees from 1935 to 1938 and again from 1943 to 1947, Business Committees from 1939 to 1942, and Conference Chairmen and Committee Chairmen in 1948-1949. The Local Committees were temporary and located in whatever city was host to the annual conference that year. The second subseries is the Diocesan Directors of Catholic Charities, 1932-2007, filed chronologically, in boxes 135-149. The Diocesan Directors of Catholic Charities (DDCC) were considered a Topic-Business committee, albeit one of the most important. Their separation from the Board of Directors was confirmed in the Executive Committee Minutes of 1949. The most important subcommittee of the DDCC was the Continuing Committee which was renamed the Standing Committee in 1940. The third subseries is Conference of Religious, 1920-1973, filed loosely alphabetically by subject, in boxes 150-161. The Conference of Religious was composed of sisters and had a Standing Committee and a New York office. The fourth subseries is the Committee on Professional Education for Social Work, 1934-1949, in box 162. The fifth is Aging, 1944-1988, in boxes 163-170. The sixth is Adoption, 1943-1976, in boxes 170-175. The seventh is Child Care 1925-1960, in boxes 175-176. The eighth is Disaster Relief, 1966-1990, in boxes 177-178. The ninth is United Way, 1967-1983, in boxes 179-181. The tenth and last subseries is Miscellaneous, 1967-1996, in box 182
The fifth series is Study and Survey Files, 1925-2001, in boxes 183-197, and divided into five subseries. The first is the Cadre Study, 1967-1976, in boxes 183-187. The second is Diocesan Agency Studies, 1962-1984, in box 188. The third is Foreign Studies, 1946-1984, in boxes 189-193. The fourth is State (U.S.) Studies, 1925-1961, in boxes 194-195. The fifth is Miscellaneous Studies, 1925-1982, in boxes 195-197.
The sixth series contains the Institute for Catholic Prison Chaplains/Institutional Chaplains Files, 1931-1960, in boxes 198-199. This series highlights the work of NCCC with The Commission on Prison Chaplains of the Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America. Among the chief concerns was that every Catholic prisoner in a penal or correctional institution have access to a prison chaplain.
The seventh series is Legislative Files, 1914(1928-1988)n.d., in boxes 200-236, and is divided into three subseries. The first is the Congressional Bills and Related Materials series, 1937-1977, in boxes 200-204, which consists mainly of legislation sponsored either by the Senate, House, or as joint legislation; presidential remarks delivered to Congress; and correspondence, typed remarks, and other materials related to Catholic Charities response to the legislation. The second, Legislation Subject Files, 1949-1988, in boxes 204-233, makes up the bulk of this series. The series includes alphabetical topics related to federal or state legislation, as well as NCCC and Catholic Charities USA legislative materials. Of note are files on abortion, pluralism, social security, and welfare reform. The final series, State and Local Legislation, 1914(1928-1984)n.d., in boxes 234-236, includes files on legislation of interest to the CCUSA outside the federal level. The first section of material includes files by state, followed by files by subject, including adoption, juvenile delinquency, and unemployment.
The eighth series is Audiovisual materials, 1910-2006, in boxes 237-258, and is divided into five subseries. The first is Photographs, 1910-2006, which contain photographs, negatives, contact sheets and photographs on compact disks of individuals, events, and causes related to Catholic Charities USA. These include portraits of Monsignor John O'Grady, as well as O'Grady with others. There are also numerous unidentified photographs. Subseries two is Slides, 1970s-2002, which include slide shows on CCUSA's Vision 2000 project, as well as its Parish Outreach Project and staff photos. Subseries three is video tapes and filmstrips, 1977-2005, which include VHS, U-matic, Beta, and video cassettes of CCUSA conferences, television appearances, public service announcements, and projects. Subseries four is cassettes, 1976-2002, which include recordings of CCUSA conferences, as well as 92 loose cassettes of miscellaneous CCUSA conferences or programs. Subseries five is Oversize material, 1910-1961, includes panoramas and oversize photographs from Catholic Charities meetings and unidentified events, as well as portraits of Bishops William A. O'Connor and Bryan McEntegart, a photo of Pope Pius XII, a letter from Pope Pius XI to Msgr. O'Grady, and a degree and certificates belonging to O'Grady.
The ninth series is Publications, 1910-2015, in boxes 259-294. This includes printed proceedings and annual reports as well as journals Catholic Charities Review and Social Thought, not to mention the magazine Charities USA. Boxes 259-275 have been processed, with the contents listed online. The more general and miscellanous publications in boxes 276-294 are still being processed. For content and access questions please email archives@mail.lib.cua.edu.
The tenth and final series is Awards, undated, in box 295. This is currently in process, for content and access questions please email archives@mail.lib.cua.edu.
Arrangement
The Catholic Charities USA records consist of 10 Series.
Series 1: Early Records, 1910-1918, Box 1
Series 2: Board of Directors Minutes and Related Papers, 1925(1925-1988)2004, Boxes 1-11
Series 3: General Administration Files, 1920-2008, Boxes 12-111
Series 4: Committee Files, 1920-2007, Boxes 112-182
Series 5: Study and Survey Files, 1925-2001, Boxes 183-197
Series 6: Institute for Catholic Prison Chaplains/Institutional Chaplains Files, 1931-1960, Boxes 198-199
Series 7: Legislation Files, 1914(1928-1988)n.d., Boxes 200-236
Series 8: Audiovisual, 1910-2010, Boxes 237-258
Series 9: Publications, 1910-2015, Boxes 259-294
Series 10: Awards,n.d., Box 295
Restrictions on Access
25 years or living persons, except for restricted adoption or other case file(s) in boxes 162, 170, and 176.
Related Material
The American Catholic History Research Center and University Archives:
Marquette University, Special Collections and University Archives:
Catholic Social Action Collection
The University of Minnesota has:
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Alinsky, Saul; Corcoran, Lawrence; Gallagher, Raymond J.; Harvey, Thomas; Kammer, Frederick; Kerby, William J., 1870-1936; LeBlond, Charles Joseph, Bishop of St. Joseph, Missouri; Mason, Florence; Mellen, Francis; O'Grady, John J., 1886-1966; Padgett, Alice; Shahan, Thomas J.; Snyder, Larry
Organizations:
Catholic Charities USA; Catholic Hospital Association; Catholic University of America (CUA); Child Welfare League of America; Family Welfare Association; Federal Security Agency; Federal Works Agency; National Catholic Rural Life Conference; National Catholic Welfare Conference; National Commission on Children and Youth; National Committee on Aging; National Conference of Catholic Charities; National Health Insurance; National Housing Conference; Society of St. Vincent de Paul; United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW); United States Department of Labor; Urban Coalition
Places:
Albany, New York; Alexandria, Virginia; Baltimore, Maryland; Cleveland, Ohio; Detroit, Michigan; Los Angeles, California; Milwaukee, Wisconsin; New York, New York; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; St. Louis, Missouri; Toledo, Ohio; Washington, D.C.
Subjects:
Adoption; Aging; Agriculture; Child Care; Church Charities; Disaster Relief; Housing; Juvenile Delinquency; Pluralism; Prisons; Social Action; Social Security; War on Poverty; Welfare Reform
Acquisition Information
Shortly after the death of Msgr. John O'Grady, Secretary of the National Conference of Catholic Charities (NCCC) from 1920 to 1961, Catholic University of America (CUA) Archivist Rev. Michael Hall wrote to Msgr. Lawrence Corcoran, the current Secretary, to inquire about the possibility of depositing O'Grady's papers at CUA. Hall argued that these would be a fine addition to related collections such as the papers of William Kerby, Francis Haas, and John A. Ryan. However, NCCC took no action at this time. In 1969, the University of Minnesota inquired about the NCCC records for their Social Welfare Archives, and Marquette University was also said to be interested in acquiring these same records. Through the work of both Dorothy Bird Daly and Dorothy Mohler of CUA's National Catholic School of Social Service (NCSSS) the NCCC records were pledged to CUA at the annual meeting of the NCCC board of directors in October 1972. These records began to come to CUA in 1977 though NCCC retained ownership, including copyright. It was also understood that said records would have a restriction of 25 years or living persons, although it was not until February of 2002 however that a formal deed of gift agreement was signed between Catholic Charities USA (the named was changed in 1986) and CUA. Some 13 boxes, about 17 linear feet, of personal papers of Msgr. John J. O'Grady were removed in 2013 and set up as a separate (but closely related) archival collection at CUA.
Bibliography
Brown, Dorothy M., and Elizabeth McKeown. The poor belong to Us: Catholic Charities and American Welfare. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 1997.
Frydl, Kathleen J. 'The Criminalization of Distress: The Government's Response to Foundlings in the Postwar United States,' The Journal of Policy History, Vo. 26, No.2, 2014: 188-218.
Gavin, Donald P. The National Conference of Catholic Charities. Milwaukee, WI: Catholic Life Publications, 1962.
Hehir, J. Bryan. (ed). Catholic Charities USA: 100 Years at the Intersection of Charity and Justice. Collegeville, MN: Liturgical Press, 2010.
Kerby, William J. The Social Mission of Charity: A Study of Points of View in Catholic Charities. New York: MacMillan, 1921
Lescher, Bruce H. The Spiritual Life and Social Action in American Catholic Spirituality: William J. Kerby and Paul Hanly Furfey. Ph.D. Dissertation, Graduate Theological Union, 1991.
O'Grady, John J. Catholic Charities in the United States: History and Problems. Washington, D.C.: National Conference of Catholic Charities, 1931.
Tifft, Thomas W. Toward A More Humane Social Policy: The Work and Influence of Monsignor John O'Grady, Ph.D dissertation. Washington, D.C. 1979.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1: Early Records, 1910-1918; (1 Box)
  Miscellaneous surviving materials from the tenure of William J. Kerby.
  - Address of Samuel Gompers at The Catholic University of America (CUA), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Edmond Butler to Thomas Shahan on First National Conference, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: William J. Kerby, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Subjects: 1912 Report and 1914 Conference Dues
  - Correspondence: William J. Kerby, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Proceedings: First National Conference of Catholic Charities at The Catholic University of America (CUA), September 25-28, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1916, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Board of Directors - Minutes and Related Papers, 1925-1986, 2004; (11 Boxes)
  The Board was known as the 'Executive Committee' prior to 1950 when the name was changed to 'Board of Directors.' Filed chronologically.
  - Subseries 2.1: Executive Committee/Board of Directors, 1925-1986; (8 Boxes)
    - Executive Committee - Minutes, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Executive Committee - Minutes, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Executive Committee - Minutes, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Executive Committee - Minutes, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)